<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Etienne Burdet</title>
    <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Etienne Burdet</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 19:52:53 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://etienneburdet.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Forked City</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/forked/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 19:52:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/forked/</guid>
      <description>A recent passion of mine has been the DAO-hardfork of the Ethereum blockchain. Especially the fact that both blockchains co-exist a month after the fork… with the same people on both chains.
If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand a single word of what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about, let me me use a smartcity exemple. Imagine a fleet of solar powered autonomous bus—that&amp;rsquo;s for the futuristic effect, it works with regular buses too—that go from charging stations to points where people have called the bus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masdar is gonna be as efficient as Besançon-Viotte</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/masdar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 19:55:30 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/masdar/</guid>
      <description>So it seems like Masdar is not going to be anywhere near net zero. Not like it&amp;rsquo;s much of a surprise to anybody. But the new figure of 50% brings back many questions, most of them old. How do you compute this number for a full city? Is Masdar going to be a city at all? Is it any good by the way?
Coming out with the embodied energy of a city is quite difficult, mainly because of the way you estimate the lifespan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ultimate scientifically true definition of the smartcity. By me.</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/definition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 19:55:30 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/definition/</guid>
      <description>No less than that. Ready? Here we go:
A part of a city is smart when its elements communicate with the TCP/IP protocol.
That&amp;rsquo;s it folks. Hmm… I feel a bit of disappointment. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound futuristic enough? Too technocratic maybe? Let&amp;rsquo;s look deeper.
First, does it work? Since TCP/IP powers the internet, we have: internet of things, people gathering over social network, Uber, Airbnb and Bitcoin, big data and monitoring, participatory politics etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Musk &amp; The City</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/musk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2016 17:43:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/musk/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s funny, I was re-reading Jan Ghel&amp;rsquo;s Cities for People when they announced BIG and Foster would design the Hype&amp;reg;loop stations. On one side, the vision of pedestrian city centers, human scale furniture and small distances. On the other, the vision of huge oddly shaped perfume boxes, infinite corridors, elevators and speed of light travel. All of a sudden something became clear to me: Elon Musk has bet on the end of the cities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3615 Smart City</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/3615/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 17:43:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/3615/</guid>
      <description>Since yesterday, it&amp;rsquo;s all the rage for CityMapper, Transit and the like in Paris. The RATP has decided to close back their data, until they really re-open it again late 2016. The official reason is that &amp;ldquo;RATP is thinking about a way to monetize his data&amp;rdquo;. This problem is not specific to the RATP actually, but may apply to anything smartcity and is as old as the profitable internet. I call it the &amp;ldquo;Minitel way of the smartcity&amp;rdquo; issue (for the non-french of you, read what the Minitel was).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critique of Opens Source Architecture by Carlo Ratti</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/oascritique/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 07:30:19 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/oascritique/</guid>
      <description>Open Source Architecture is a book by Carlo Ratti, on what happens to architecture in this flat networked movement that is taking up the world, from open source software to 3D printing over the internet—or cooperative energy I might even add! Written by someone who started his career on urban morphology and energy, now turned to smart cities (see a pattern?), you guess I was interested.
Rather than jumping straight into “hey, you see Wikipedia and Raspberry Pi ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does a smartcity officer do ?</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/jobupdate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 07:30:19 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/jobupdate/</guid>
      <description>A quick site update to reflect my new position as a smart-city officer at AREP. Which leads to a natural question:What does a smart-city officer do, beside having a job with a really cool job name ?
First you have the top-down approach to my work. Here, somebody (a stakeholder, a politic) comes to us and say &amp;ldquo;Hey, I heard smart-cities are cool. I want mine. You make it?. Sure we do but… is he speaking participatory urban planning or driverless cars or smartgrids ?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 21:50:49 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&amp;rarr; My Résumé I&amp;rsquo;m an urban engineer, currently doing smartcity R&amp;amp;D at AREP. My work is to help everybody about all thoses new connected things, should they be architect or electrical engineer, and make sure they make sense for an architectural project. Before that, I did research on the relation between energy fluxes and urban morphology at EIVP and CSTB. I also work on various side-topics regarding urban morphology, urban design/planning and urban climate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Article Update</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/articleupdate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/articleupdate/</guid>
      <description>The article on the thermal part of my model has been reviewed quite quickly. I updated the version with some minors modifications, you can find it on my HAL profile (moderation pending) and arXiv. I hope it&amp;rsquo;s useful, feel free to ask any question.
The hardest part was maybe to understand how to properly submit a LaTeX article through EES. It&amp;rsquo;s well made in fact, you upload your .tex and .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Here Hugo</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/hugo/</guid>
      <description>Whether for a personal page or a project site, we need websites all the time, to be someone on the web. We want something simple, but we don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have the money to hire a pro (when we should) – but hey, this shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that hard. So what do we have ? A tumblr, wordpress.com ? Hosting your own wordpress or drupal ? WYSIWYG tools ?
For this web site, I chose a static generator: Hugo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Site Opening</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/open/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 23:34:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/post/open/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to do this for far too long, here it is: I have my own website !
So what to expect here ? First the usual hub: vita, publications, social links. Nothings you couldn&amp;rsquo;t find on my lab&amp;rsquo;s site or linkedin, but this can&amp;rsquo;t be in too many places.
But a personal site should be, well, a bit more personal. So I listed here some resources, like templates and a few readings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Reading Bundle</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/readings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 14:28:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/readings/</guid>
      <description>I realized that whenever I talk about my work, I end up giving a list of pretty standard books, rather than the latest new fancy thing in my feeds. They are not my daily read, neither my only reading topic. It is more a minimal list of the basics of my discipline. It should give you a good sense of where I&amp;rsquo;m from.
If you had only one to read  Cities and Forms: On Sustainable Urbanism : The big bad guy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/resources/</guid>
      <description>Latex : My PhD. memoir template, my fork of Deedy&amp;rsquo;s CV.
My reading bundle : To get started on urban morphology and energy modeling.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>