<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Recent Content on Etienne Burdet </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/index.xml</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 16:39:37 CET</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Here Hugo</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/2014/11/herehugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 16:39:37 CET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/2014/11/herehugo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Whether for a personal page or a project site, we need websites all the time, to be someone on the web. We want something simple, but we don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have the money to hire a pro (when we should) – but hey, this shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that hard. So what do we have ? A tumblr, wordpress.com ? Hosting your own wordpress or drupal ? WYSIWYG tools ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this web site, I chose a static generator: &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. Why ? You Input text files, it outputs a full – super lightweight and responsive – plain html site. Magic happens in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Be cool, be static&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those hipsterish days, old is the new cool and apparently we are back to static sites. Or static generator to be more precise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does the thing works ? First I installed Hugo (it takes about 2 clicks) and told him &amp;ldquo;new site please&amp;rdquo;. He gave me a backbone, empty site. Now when I want to input a new page, or a new blog post, I write the content in &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/markdown-basics/&#34;&gt;markdown&lt;/a&gt; in a text file and… that&amp;rsquo;s about it. Then you say &amp;ldquo;hey Hugo, make a site out this bunch of text files&amp;rdquo;, and then he generates a whole site in milliseconds. A fully static, ready to upload website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That simple ? That simple. Then you can customize the template, by digging a bit into the HTML/CSS/Go template. It is hackable to the core. The really great thing being the learning curve. Simple things — such as the social button — are simple to do and from there you can gradually tweak your site more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Ligh, flexible and free&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First advantage: no database. No php, no CMS, no accounts, no nothing server side. Read: no bugs. Just plain html pages that you upload on any host. No account on a specific service either (like wordpress.com), which means no adds, no terms of use, no limitations of any kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second advantage is in the long run. What will tumblr or about.me be in 10 years ? What is gonna happen when I need to transfer my site from wordpress.com to the new cool thing ? One thing is sure, plain html is gonna be here for a long time. This site is hosted on github, but if I want it on dropbox or any other host, I upload the file there and it is up in minutes, literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Mobile first, content first&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to go for the superb &lt;a href=&#34;http://andhyde.com/&#34;&gt;Hyde&lt;/a&gt; theme. It is responsive (try resize that window) and it&amp;rsquo;s mobile first/content first. It means you don&amp;rsquo;t have one hundred links on the sidebar, you don&amp;rsquo;t have the avatar of every single guy who likes the page on the facebook, no wordcloud, no widgets everywhere, etc. Deliver the content efficiently, else it&amp;rsquo;s gonna be unreadable on a small smartphone screen. And looks so clean on big one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light, fast, responsive, content first, customizable… you feel so free ! Going back to a CMS from Hugo for this kind of site would just feel like riding a limo on bike path.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 16:49:42 CET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/EtienneBurdet_CV.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;rarr; My Résumé&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a 28 years old PhD. candidate (soon a Dr. !) in urban engineering at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eivp-paris.fr/&#34;&gt;EIVP&lt;/a&gt;. My main research is focused on the relation between energy fluxes and urban morphology. I try to produce models for engineers, designers or anybody trying to build cities, rather than for external observers. I also work on various side-topics regarding urban morphology, urban design/planning and urban climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how I look in my natural habitat :
&lt;img src=&#34;/me.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I exist for real&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beside research, I traded my living room for movie theaters, I hunt art exhibitions, dance and new circus performances in Paris, I&amp;rsquo;m a huge tea/wine/food/restaurants geek and a passionate snowboarder.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/Resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 15:57:37 CET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/Resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This section is under construction. It should fill up quickly !&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Latex :&lt;/strong&gt; My &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/etienneburdet/Phd-template&#34;&gt;PhD. memoir template&lt;/a&gt;, my fork of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/etienneburdet/Deedy-Resume&#34;&gt;Deedy&amp;rsquo;s CV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/resources/readings&#34;&gt;My reading bundle&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/strong&gt; To get started on urban morphology and energy modeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a (hopefully growing) list of related blog posts:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Site Opening</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/2014/10/open/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 23:34:18 CEST</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/2014/10/open/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to do this for far too long, here it is: I have my own website !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what to expect here ? First the usual hub: vita, publications, social links. Nothings you couldn&amp;rsquo;t find on my lab&amp;rsquo;s site or linkedin, but this can&amp;rsquo;t be in too many places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a personal site should be, well, a bit more personal. So I listed here some resources on how I work, diverse templates, tips and a few readings. The kind of things I would tell you if we were to meet in person, but you would never ask by e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I always wanted to have some sort of irregular blog on both city science and working in the academia. Half scientific things that doesn&amp;rsquo;t really fit journals, comments on articles, discussion on research itself (read: surviving a PhD), productivity at work, etc. I want to write on all those topics and I think it&amp;rsquo;s the ideal place to so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this site last in the long run, survives institutions and lab changes. I hope it gives you some useful infos and – who knows – maybe some fun. Enjoy your visit and feel free to share your feelings on this site !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Reading Bundle</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/resources/readings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 14:28:36 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/resources/readings/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I realized that whenever I talk about my work, I end up giving a list of pretty standard books, rather than the latest new fancy thing in my feeds. They are not my daily read, neither my only reading topic. It is more a minimal list of the basics of my discipline. It should give you a good sense of where I&amp;rsquo;m from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;If you had only one to read&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Cities-Forms-On-Sustainable-Urbanism/dp/2705681116/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1414488270&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=serge+salat&#34;&gt;Cities and Forms: On Sustainable Urbanism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; : The big bad guy. I was in Serge&amp;rsquo;s lab when he wrote this and he is kind of my mentor. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure it&amp;rsquo;s readable straight from start to finish and I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily endorse all views. But the amount of information in this book is just incredible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Morphology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.fr/Urban-Housing-Handbook-Eric-Firley/dp/1119989981&#34;&gt;The Urban Housing Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; : before anything, look at what has been done in the world. Excellent maps and essential figures on density. Follow-up on towers and master planning are definitely worth reading too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Streets-Patterns-Stephen-Marshall/dp/0415317509&#34;&gt;Streets &amp;amp; Patterns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Once again a broad view, not super technical. Just make sure you have all those pictures in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Space-Matrix-Density-Urban-Form/dp/9056627422&#34;&gt;Space Matrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; : Are you sure you know you basic arithmetics of urban morpho&amp;rsquo; ? Super simple, still essential for good problem setting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Urban Energy Modeling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.fr/Computer-Modelling-Sustainable-Urban-Design/dp/1844076792&#34;&gt;Computer Modeling For Sustainable Urban Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; : everything urban energy modeling, state of the art (the few newly published things doesn&amp;rsquo;t really change the game).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few articles: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0378-7788(02)00079-8&#34;&gt;Ratti 2003&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0378778804003391&#34;&gt;Ratti 2005&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0038092X06000612&#34;&gt;Robinson 2006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, for passive volume, perimeter blocks and irregular irradiation patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Modeling Epistemology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcxapc.org/inserts/ouvrages/0609tsgtm.pdf&#34;&gt;Théorie du Système Général - Théorie de la Modélisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; : why are we even modeling ? This book is my base on systemic, on complex systems and more broadly on why I&amp;rsquo;m not modeling like a physicist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.wiley.com/10.1111/ecoj.12128&#34;&gt;Economic Models as Analogy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: a primer on case-based reasoning and analogy interpretation of models. Initially for economy, it works really well for city modeling too (found this one on James Keirstead&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jameskeirstead.ca/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, remember that it is a very minimal list, nothing exhaustive. But it should get you started on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/Publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2014 16:47:33 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/Publications/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Journal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burdet, E., Colombert, M, Morand, D. Diab, Y. &lt;strong&gt;Integrated canopy, building energy and radiosity model for 3D urban design.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Energy and Buildings&lt;/em&gt;, 2014, (submitted). &lt;a href=&#34;(https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01075816&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-link&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Conference Papers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burdet, E., Colombert, M, Morand, D. Diab, Y. &lt;a href=&#34;http://mediatum.ub.tum.de/node?id=1169330&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modeling of Energy Fluxes for Urban Designs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PLEA 2013 Sustainable Architecture for a Renewable Future&lt;/em&gt;, 2013 (Munich, Germany). &lt;a href=&#34;http://mediatum.ub.tum.de/node?id=1169330&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-link&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;rarr; Note : with hydrodynamic mobility model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burdet, E., Colombert, M, Morand, D. Diab, Y. &lt;strong&gt;Methodology for the Life Cycle Energy Assessment of Urban Designs&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ecobalance 2012 Challenges and Solutions for Sustainable Society&lt;/em&gt;, 2012 (Yokohama, Japan).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burdet, E., Colombert, M, Morand, D. Diab, Y. &lt;strong&gt;Modélisation des Flux Énergétiques Urbains pour les Projets d’Aménagements&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Futurs Urbains&lt;/em&gt;, 2012 (Yokohama, Japan). &lt;a href=&#34;http://villes-environnement.fr/fr/login.html&#34;&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-link&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;rarr; Note : different mobility model compared to the PLEA 2013 paper (otherwise similar but in french).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burdet, E., Colombert, M, Morand, D. Diab, Y. &lt;strong&gt;Modèle multicouche couplé Bâti - Canopée urbaine&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;30 ème rencontres de l&amp;rsquo;Association Universitaire de Génie Civil&lt;/em&gt;, 2013 (Cachan, France).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Thesis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Phd. (Dir. Youssef Diab): &lt;strong&gt;Energy Model for Urban Morphology Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;rarr; out soon… under review !&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Master&amp;rsquo;s (Dir. Serge Salat): &lt;strong&gt;Mathematicaly Based Taxonomy of Urban Morphologies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This document is more or less in the purgatory. We were supposed to make a book out of it, but never happened and the thesis in itself is not really publishable. Available on request if you are really interested. The content is a bit like Marshall&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Street &amp;amp; Patterns&lt;/em&gt;, but for groups of buildings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>