<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Productivity on Etienne Burdet </title>
      <generator uri="https://gohugo.io">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/tags/productivity/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 16:39:37 CET</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Here Hugo</title>
      <link>http://etienneburdet.github.io/2014/11/herehugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 16:39:37 CET</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://etienneburdet.github.io/2014/11/herehugo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Whether for a personal page or a project site, we need websites all the time, to be someone on the web. We want something simple, but we don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have the money to hire a pro (when we should) – but hey, this shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be that hard. So what do we have ? A &lt;em&gt;tumblr&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;wordpress.com&lt;/em&gt; ? Hosting your own &lt;em&gt;wordpress&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;drupal&lt;/em&gt; ? &lt;em&gt;WYSIWYG&lt;/em&gt; tools ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this web site, I chose a static generator: &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. Why ? You Input text files, it outputs a full – super lightweight and responsive – plain html site. Magic happens in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Be cool, be static&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those hipsterish days, old is the new cool and apparently we are back to static sites. Or static generator to be more precise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does the thing works ? First I installed Hugo (it takes about 2 clicks) and told him &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;new site please&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. He gave me a backbone, empty site. Now when I want to input a new page, or a new blog post, I write the content in a text file using &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/markdown-basics/&#34;&gt;markdown&lt;/a&gt; and… that&amp;rsquo;s about it. Then you say &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;hey Hugo, make a site out of this bunch of text files&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; and he generates a whole site in milliseconds. A fully static, ready to upload website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That simple ? That simple. You can customize the template, by digging a bit into the HTML/CSS/Go template. It is hackable to the core. The really great thing being the learning curve. Simple things — such as the social button — are simple to do and from there you can gradually tweak your site more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Ligh, flexible and free&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First advantage: no database. No php, no CMS, no accounts, no nothing server side. Read: no bugs. Just plain html pages that you upload on any host. No account on a specific service either (like wordpress.com), which means no adds, no terms of use, no limitations of any kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second advantage is in the long run. What will &lt;em&gt;tumblr&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;about.me&lt;/em&gt; be in 10 years ? What is gonna happen when I need to transfer my site from &lt;em&gt;wordpress.com&lt;/em&gt; to the new cool thing ? One thing is sure, plain html is gonna be here for a long time. This site is hosted on github, but if I want it on dropbox or any other host, I upload the file there and it is up in minutes, literally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Mobile first, content first&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to go for the superb &lt;a href=&#34;http://andhyde.com/&#34;&gt;Hyde&lt;/a&gt; theme. It is responsive (try resize that window) and it&amp;rsquo;s mobile first/content first. It means you don&amp;rsquo;t have one hundred links on the sidebar, you don&amp;rsquo;t have the avatar of every single guy who likes the page on the facebook, no wordcloud, no widgets everywhere, etc. Deliver the content efficiently, else it&amp;rsquo;s gonna be unreadable on a small smartphone screen. And it looks so clean on big one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light, fast, responsive, content first, customizable… I feel so free ! Going back to a CMS from Hugo for this kind of site would just feel like riding a limo on bike path.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>